## Shawn Roberts, M.A.Sc.

# Unit 2, 118 Braemar Avenue, Toronto, Ontario

Ph: 289-971-7886, Email: <a href="mailto:sroberts9997@gmail.com">sroberts9997@gmail.com</a>

# Senior Project Manager/ Environmental Scientist

17+ Years Experience • Climate Change • Environmental Impact Assessment Oil and Gas • Mining • Manufacturing

## **Professional Summary**

Shawn Roberts is an environmental advisor and project manager with a Masters of Applied Science in Environmental Engineering from Memorial University of Newfoundland. Shawn has more than 17 years of environmental consulting experience throughout Canada including; Ontario, Quebec, British Columbia, Alberta and Saskatchewan.

He is an environmental specialist with expertise in Environmental Impact assessment, Green House Gas Quantification, Carbon Footprinting, Sustainability, Dispersion Modelling, Permitting and Approvals, Regulatory Compliance, and Annual Reporting. His experience occurs over many industries including, oil and gas, forestry, mining, manufacturing and processing, and institutional. He has acted as the subject matter expert for environmental impact assessments at the provincial and federal levels, and has been a 3<sup>rd</sup> party reviewer for several environmental impact assessments.

#### **Education**

- Master of Environmental Engineering (M.A.Sc.), Memorial University of Newfoundland, 2001
- Bachelor of Science in Environmental Biology (B.Sc. (Hons)), Memorial University of Newfoundland, 1999

#### **Professional Experience**

#### Senior Project Manager, Pinchin Ltd., 2018 to Present

- Providing expertise in Greenhouse Gas (GHG) quantification for carbon footprints and sustainability reporting under provincial and federal regulations
- Providing solutions for clients in reducing carbon footprint and waste prevention
- Preparing and reviewing Environmental Compliance Approval (ECA) applications and Environmental Activity
  Sector Registration (EASR) preparation
- Preparing federal and provincial annual reporting requirements (NPRI, O. Reg 127, ChemTrac)
- Business development for air quality and noise in Ontario and Alberta

## Part-Time Professor, George Brown College, 2017 to Present

Teaching Environmental Science and Introduction to Geography Courses

#### Team Lead Technical - Air Quality Advisor, Matrix Solutions Inc., 2011 to 2016

- Served as technical lead for air quality team and responsible for technical integrity of projects
- Worked as project manager for intermediate to large size environmental impact assessments
- Managed project scoping, budgeting, progress reporting, project team coordination, work delegation and client liaison

- Provided technical support for preparing regulatory applications to AUC, ERCB, AESRD, BC MoE, OGC, NEB and ON MOECC
- Developed and maintained air emissions inventory for criteria air contaminants, VOC, metals and GHGs
- Created Standard Operating Procedures and Guidelines for environmental programs
- Applied dispersion modelling to assess the effect of emissions ground level concentrations, human health, odours, PAI (potential acid input) and nitrogen deposition
- Worked with clients to develop mitigation measures and sustainable approaches to environmental issues
- Mentored junior environmental engineers and scientists

## Senior Environmental Advisor, Husky Energy, 2011

- Provided technical and regulatory advice for environmental approvals and compliance group
- Reviewed environmental consultant reports and provided technical feedback
- Obtained environmental permits and approvals for projects through liaison with regulators and stakeholders
- Participated in internal meetings between business groups regarding environmental issues and impacts on business units
- Served on external committees representing Husky on air quality, climate change and greenhouse gas issues
- Reviewed proposals and selected contractors for environmental assessment projects

## Senior Air Quality Specialist, RWDI Inc., 2006 to 2010

- Managed various air quality and energy assessments from both technical and project management standpoints
- Served as discipline lead for several environmental impact assessments for oil sands projects
- Developed corporate technical methodology for air quality assessments in Alberta
- Mentored junior environmental staff and aided in their technical development
- Served as client contact for projects and provided regulatory and technical advice
- Used WRF to determine meteorological changes due to introduction of an hydroelectric dam
- Used CMAC to analyze secondary particulates over Northern Alberta

### Air Quality Specialist, Levelton Consultants, 2001 to 2005

- Provided technical leadership and guidance to Environment and Energy Group
- Served as Project Manager for environmental assessments,
- · Provided regulatory advice for clients regarding reporting requirements and approvals
- Developed QA/QC protocols for environmental assessments and audits
- Conducted dispersion modelling using CALPUFF and AERMOD for oil and gas, energy, transportation and manufacturing projects
- Prepared reports and data for environmental hearings

## **Professional Development**

Project Management Training, Matrix Solutions., 2012

© Pinchin Ltd. Page 2 of 3

- Project Management Workshop, Kelley-Mason Inc., 2007
- VBA Programming, CTC, 2007
- Stack Sampling and CEMS Workshop, Walter Smith and Associates, 2005
- CALMET/CALPUFF Certificate, 3-day, EarthTech., 2004
- Workplace Hazardous Materials Information System (WHMIS) Training, Pinchin Ltd., Annually
- Health and Safety Training, Pinchin Ltd., Annually

## **Publications and Presentations**

- Nest-Site Characteristics of Northern Waterthrushes, 2004
- Long-Term SO<sub>2</sub> Dispersion Modeling over a Coastal Region, 2003
- Response to Clear-Cut Logging by Northern Watherthrushes, 2003

© Pinchin Ltd. Page 3 of 3